Think of the UK and you’ll probably think of London.
一想到英国，你可能就会想到伦敦。
Picture France and you’ll no doubt conjure up images of Paris and its iconic Eiffel Tower.
一提到法国，毫无疑问你脑海中就会浮现出巴黎和其标志性建筑埃菲尔铁塔的画面。
To many, capital cities define a country.
对许多人来说，首都代表着一个国家。
They’re often the seat of power, the economic and political hub and sometimes the home to royalty - along with millions of city dwellers.
它们通常是权力中心、经济和政治枢纽，有时还是皇室的居所——同时居住着数百万城市居民。
For a place with so much influence, it’s important to get its location right.
对于一个拥有如此大影响力的地方，选址至关重要。
Sometimes we have to look into history to find the reasons why a capital city ended up where it did.
有时我们必须回顾历史，才能找到首都最终定址的原因。
The site of what is now London was by the river: easy to settle, easy for trading and easy to defend.
今天我们所熟知的伦敦紧邻河流：易于定居、便于贸易且易守难攻。
However, it’s not located in the country’s centre and there’s often criticism from far-flung corners of the nation that they are forgotten by the decision makers in the capital.
然而，它并不位于英国的地理中心，因此经常有来自国家偏远地区的批评声音，称他们被首都的决策者所忽视。
Other countries have taken a different approach by establishing their capitals in the geographical centre so they can exert control and project unity, like Madrid in Spain for example.
其他国家则采取了不同的策略，将首都设立在地理中心，以便实施管控并彰显国家统一，例如西班牙的马德里。
Occasionally, there have been reasons to relocate a capital.
偶尔也会有迁移首都的理由。
St Petersburg, founded by Peter the Great in 1703, was Russia’s capital from 1712-1918, before the government changed it to Moscow.
圣彼得堡由彼得大帝于1703年建立，1712年至1918年间一直是俄罗斯的首都，之后政府将首都迁到了莫斯科。
This was partly because Moscow was more central, and the government decided it was less likely to be invaded by another country.
部分原因是莫斯科地理位置更居中，而且政府认为其被他国入侵的风险更低。
And now in Indonesia there are plans to move its capital, Jakarta.
如今，印度尼西亚也计划迁移其首都雅加达。
Its new location is yet to be decided, but the reason for the move is that this megacity is sinking at one of the fastest rates in the world.
新首都的选址尚未确定，但迁移的原因是这座特大城市正以全球最快的速度之一下沉。
It’s been built on very swampy land and isn’t helped by lots of groundwater being extracted to use for drinking water and washing.
雅加达建在一片非常泥泞的沼泽地上，而大量抽取地下水用于饮用和清洗的行为更是加剧了这一问题。
The city is overcrowded too and roads are often gridlocked.
这座城市人口过于拥挤，道路也经常拥堵。
Of course, if you can’t move your capital city, why not construct a brand new one?
当然，如果你无法迁移现有的首都，为什么不新建一座呢？
Brazil moved its capital from coastal, crowded Rio de Janeiro to inland Brasilia in 1961 - the idea being to build a brand new capital "to bring progress to the interior of Brazil", as architect Oscar Niemeyer described it.
1961年，巴西将首都从沿海拥挤的里约热内卢迁至内陆城市巴西利亚——正如建筑师奥斯卡·尼迈耶所描述的那样，建造这座全新首都的初衷是“为巴西内陆地区带来发展”。
And more recently, Nay Pyi Taw was built in 2005 as Myanmar’s new capital.
更近的例子是2005年内比都成为了缅甸的新首都。
This remote city is four times the size of London and has huge roads, golf courses and a zoo – but few people.
这座偏远的城市面积是伦敦的四倍，拥有宽阔的道路、高尔夫球场和动物园——但人口却寥寥无几。